today we're going to learn how to build
the beta and you guys are going to get
to do this as part of lab 5 so by the
time you're done with lab 5 you will
have actually built a 32-bit
microprocessor which is pretty exciting
so probably don't need to remind anybody
that quiz 2 is tomorrow the only thing
is that I would like to remind people of
is that you should try to go to your
assigned section so that we make sure to
have enough seats for everybody to take
the exam ok so before we get started
with talking about how it is that we're
going to design the hardware for the
beta let's think a little bit about what
goals we want to satisfy in our design
so first of all of course we care about
functionality right so it must work
correctly but in addition to working
correctly there are a couple other
things that we want to think of so the
first thing is that we might want to
maximize performance of our beta and so
how do we think about this measuring
this performance we measure it in terms
of instructions that we execute per
second and specifically we use the term
MIPS which stands for millions of
instructions per second as a way of of
essentially rating how good a processor
is another thing that we might want to
consider is the cost of developing this
processor and cost of integrated
circuits is directly proportional to the
its size so the smaller we can make it
the cheaper it's going to be and finally
we might want some kind of combination
of the two where we care about the
performance that you can get per unit
cost and if we're dealing with
applications which happen to care about
power like for example devices that that
need to be small then we're also going
to care about how our performance
changes with regards to power
consumption
okay so performance is inversely
proportional to the amount of time that
it takes to run our program so let's
think about what are the three things
that are going to affect the amount of
time it takes to run our program so the
first is the number of instructions in
our program okay so if we add some
really complicated instructions for
example something that might allow you
to add to values from memory and store
the result right back into memory as a
single instruction it's possible that
you could make your code shorter and
that's reduce the number of instructions
that you have in your program however
and so there's also a trade-off to that
which is that if you support such
complicated instructions then you know
the logic that's required in order to
decode exactly what needs to happen in
your data path and your circuitry itself
it's probably going to be more
complicated so when we talk about
reducing execution time we may want to
reduce the number of instructions but we
have to carefully think about what
that's going to do to our cycles per
instruction which is the second piece of
the puzzle okay so our time is dependent
on the average number of cycles that it
takes to execute an instruction and so
if I support instructions that are much
more complicated then chances are that
my average cycles per instruction is
going to go up so again these are sort
of trade-offs that are fighting against
each other and we need to take them into
consideration when making our design
decisions and then the third component
is cycle time okay and this is dominated
by how complicated our logic is so if
we're able to actually implement our
beta using very simple logic then we're
going to be able to reduce the clock
cycle which we can run our beta and thus
improve performance so what we're going
to present today is a simple model for
for exit for creating the hardware for
our beta and in this model the
assumption is that the clocks per
instruction R is one
okay there are ways to do better than
that you couldn't do things like
pipelining your processor you can have
better memory systems which reduce your
cycle time all sorts of things which
we're also going to get into in the next
few lectures but today we'll focus on
this more simple implementation that
assumes a clocks per instruction of what
okay
so very quick recap of what it is that
the beta does hopefully by now
everyone's pretty familiar with this so
we have four types of instructions that
are supported we have the OP type of
instructions which are basically ALU
operations that operate on two registers
we have ops C which are ALU operations
that operate on one register and a
constant we have memory operations like
load and store and we have control flow
operations like jumps and branches okay
so we've learned about what the format
is of each of these instructions and we
learned that there are two types of
instruction formats that we support the
first is one where you specify three
registers so that you can have two
registers as your source operands and
one is your destination this is used for
the OP type of operations and now we go
a little bit further in that we actually
specify a little bit more information
about our 6 bit opcode so what we're
going to do in order to differentiate
between the various classes of
instructions is we're going to use the
top 2 bits of our opcode to give us some
information about what kind of
instruction it is so specifically we'll
use 1 0 in the top two bits to indicate
that you're doing an OP instruction
which is an opera ALU operation on two
registers ok our second type of
instruction is one that uses a constant
instead of a second register and so this
will cover the OP C types of
instructions and in this case what we're
going to do is we're going to set the
top two bits of our opcode to one one in
order to identify those types of
instructions now for the remaining ones
the memory and control our instruction
format
looks the same but we will use yet
another opcode to identify those so
first let me back up a step and quickly
just summarize what it is that the ALU
is able to do and so we have four types
of operations that you guys built into
your ALU in lab 3 we have the arithmetic
type of operations we have compares we
have boolean logic and we have shift
operation okay and for each of those we
also have the comparable one that can
operate with a constant where you simply
add the c2 to this instruction name okay
so on to memory and control flow
operations here we see that we have the
same format into that sense that it uses
two registers and a constant but now
what we're going to do is we're going to
set the top two bits of our opcode to
zero one to identify that this case
covers our load and store operations as
well as our branch and jump operations
okay all right so in order to create the
hardware for our beta we're going to
take an incremental approach what we're
going to do is we're going to go through
the various types of instructions that
we need to support and add the necessary
hardware for each and then we're going
to combine the pieces as we go along
using multiplexers or whatever other
kind of logic we need to make it all
work together so we're going to start
off with our ALU instructions then we'll
add the load and store operations to
that then we'll add jump in branch
operations to that and finally we'll
also add hardware which allows us to
deal with exceptions when something goes
wrong in our program all right so the
hardware is gonna consist of some
components that you're all familiar with
at this point so one of the major
components are registers have multi bit
registers like 32-bit registers in order
to handle the fact that our data path is
32 bits wide and you'll note that these
registers are clock enabled so they
basically only load something into the
register on
rise in the clock edge okay and then
they'll hold that value for the entire
clock period we're also going to use
lots of muxes these muxes are going to
select between different portions of our
data path in order to execute the
appropriate behavior based on the type
of operation that you have we have our
ALU which is basically the ALU you built
in lab 3 and we have several types of
memories we're going to have our
register file as well as instruction and
data memories alright so let's start off
with the register file if you recall
when we first started talking about the
beta is a we drew a picture that was
pretty similar to this where we said you
have a bunch of registers and then you
have some multiplexers that can select
which of the registers you want to read
as your source operands then over here
we have a decoder that takes the address
that you want to write to and that's
used in order to select which register
you're going to write to if we zoom in
to one of these register blocks what
that actually looks like is it's a
register with an enable so what does
that mean it means that it's not always
going to load a new value into the
register on every rising clock edge but
rather it'll only do that when enable is
set to 1 okay so if enable is set to 1
we allow the new piece of data to come
through and on the next rising clock
edge that will get stored in our
register if enable is 0 we just keep the
previous value that was in our register
all right and just for simplicity we're
going to create this icon which is going
to represent this register file so
recall that we have 32 registers here
each of which is 32 bits wide so what
we're going to have in our register file
is we're going to have to read ports ok
we can read two registers at the same
time in order to specify which registers
we want to read we're going to provide a
5 bit address so if you recall in our
instruction format we had our a and our
B so you can use those
it's directly in order to address and
specify which of the registers you want
to read from your register file the
outputs which is the contents of these
registers that you selected are going to
come out here on your data ports and
each one of those outputs is going to be
32 bits wide now note that the two
addresses here are completely
independent of each other and so you
could choose to pick the same register
for RA and RB or different registers
it'll work in either way okay then we
have the controls for writing so in
order to be able to write to our
register file we have three pieces of
information in addition to having our
address just like we did for the read
we're gonna have a five bit address
which is typically the RC register that
we're specifying we're gonna have the 32
bit data which is the data that we want
to write to that specified register and
we're going to have a write enable which
is going to have to be one in order to
allow any kind of writing to happen at
all and again this whole system is
clocked so the way that this works is
that our our reads are actually
combinational so if I provide an address
to on the read address ports at some TPD
later I will get the data for the
register that I asked to read the writes
however are clocked so I provide the
right address it might be that I
provided at the beginning of the clock
cycle but that write isn't going to
actually happen until the rising edge of
the next clock and then just one other
little thing to remember is that even
though we have 32 registers we are
assuming that register 31 is always
going to produce the value 0 and so
there's also going to be some internal
logic in this register file that's going
to make sure that if you pick register
31 as the register you're reading that
the output you provide is just 0 ok so
let's take a quick look at what the
timing of our register file looks like
so as we mentioned we have two
combinational reads and one write that
happens
so the combinational reads you basically
as soon as you have the address on your
read address port TPD later you're going
to get the value of the contents of that
register on your read data port for our
writes things are a little bit more
complicated so we have three signals
that we want to worry about we want to
worry about our write enable which has
to be one in order to enable writing to
any register the right address which is
going to specify which register we were
going to write to and the write data
which is the data we actually want to
write to that register and now because
this is a clocked right we're going to
have our timing parameters T set up and
T hold so these three inputs need to be
stable and valid for T set up before the
rising edge of the clock and for T hold
after the rising edge of the clock now
assuming that we satisfy these timing
constraints then what we know will
happen is that after tpd after that
rising clock edge and these things have
have been held for the right amount of
time then we're gonna get a new value
written into our register okay
so just one thing to note here is that
the value coming out from the read data
ports can actually change for two
reasons it can change because I change
the address that I'm reading from or it
can change because I happen to do a
write to the register that I'm reading
okay any questions about that
now one thing you might ask yourself is
well what if I want to read from and
write to the same register again just
like we could read to different
registers or the same one there's
actually no problem here in everything
there's no problem is because the writes
are clocked so what's going to happen is
if these two registers are the same
you're going to read the old value of
your register in the current clock cycle
and then on the next rising clock edge
you're going to write the new value into
that same register and it will become
available for the next clock cycle okay
so let's start thinking about what do we
need to do in order to support ALU
instructions so what ALU instructions do
is fairly simple if you have an ADD for
example you're going to add the contents
of register r2 to register r3 and store
that into register r4 and our source and
destination operands are specified here
in the RCRA and our B fields and recall
notice again that our opcode begins with
the top two bits one zero two then to
indicate that this is an ALU operation
that uses two registers now what our
hardware is going to have to do is it's
going to have to execute these five
steps regardless of which type of
instruction we're using the first step
is to fetch the instruction that we're
going to execute so the way that we do
this is we have our special PC program
which holds the address of the
instruction that we should execute next
and so we fetch the instruction that's
located at the address that the PC
points to and that's the instruction
that we want to execute so the next step
is to decode that instruction so we have
to look at the opcode of that
instruction and determine what operation
it is that we need to perform in order
to execute that operation correctly
after that we need to read our source
operands and so we're going to use the
our a and our B fields or a constant if
it's a constant operation in order to to
be ready to execute using those two
operands and finally we're going to
actually execute our operation and the
last step
is we'll take the result of that
execution and write it back to our
register file so one thing you have to
realize is that the clock period at
which we're going to be able to clock
our beta is going to need to be long
enough to allow for all five of these
steps to happen for every single one of
our instructions all right so let's
begin with the instruction fetch and
decode logic okay so this is relatively
simple we start with our PC register
over here this is a 32-bit register
whose bottom two bits are always 0
because we want to point to a word
boundary so the full instruction in our
instruction memory and the value of this
PC becomes the address that we feed to
our instruction memory in order to get
to fetch the instruction that we want to
execute on that cycle if we're executing
instructions sequentially then in order
to fetch the next instruction we're
going to have to add 4 to our PC and so
we have a simple add 4 adder which just
increments PC by 4 and then that new
value is fed in on the next rising edge
of the clock so the PC in order to fetch
the next instruction we also have this
reset multiplexer here which allows you
to initialize the PC to a certain value
when you want to reset your system so
you know if it's in the middle of some
operation and you have to reset it you
can force it to go back to 0 and then
over here we have our control logic the
control logic is going to be responsible
for producing all the control signals
that will make the right things happen
in our data path and so what the control
logic is going to be set to is going to
be dependent on the 6 bit opcode that
we're going to read from the instruction
so you can think of your control logic
as basically being a read-only memory
where the address that you're feeding
into the street only memory is the 6
bits of your opcode which means that I
have 64 locations in my ROM and then the
for each location I'm going to have all
of the control signals that are we
wired for my beta and they'll be set to
different values depending on what the
opcode says all right so what is the
data path for an ALU operation look like
it's relatively it's not too complicated
we're going to need first of all a
register file we're going to need a
register file that has to read ports and
these reports are going to be used to
specify which are the two registers we
want to read and then we'll be able to
access the data from those two registers
feed it into the ALU that we've already
built and then the output of the ALU is
going to come back through the right
data port of our register file and that
will allow us to write the result of the
ALU back into our register file okay we
have the control signal ALU FN which we
need to create which is going to specify
what operation our ALU should perform
based on the opcode okay and so there is
a mapping from the opcodes to the ALU
offense which need to be fed to as the
control to your ALU and then there's one
more signal which is very important we
call it work
it stands for write an able register
file so this is the enable that we were
talking about for our rights okay so the
only way that we can actually write
something to this register file is if we
set worth equal to 1 and when worth is
equal to 1 then on their next rising
clock edge we're going to write to the
register whose address is specified by
this RC value ok and so we'll introduce
our little 6mm 4 mascot what we call him
worth because that's the control logic
input that he likes the most all right
so not so far so good
now what we want to do is we want to
augment this in order to support ALU
operations with constants so oops sorry
actually let me just show you the data
flow for the a
you operation with two registers before
we move on so essentially what's gonna
happen here is we're going to read our
two register values we're going to use
the control logic to produce the correct
control signal for the ALU that's going
to then make the ALU execute the correct
operation and then the data is going to
come back to the register file
we'll set worth equal to one to show
that we actually want to store our
results in the register file and the
data that comes out of the ALU is going
to go into the right data port of our
register file all right so now we want
to support ALU operations with constants
so this is pretty similar to what we
have saw before the difference is that
in this case we want the second operand
taken input to our ALU instead of coming
from the register file we want it to
come from the sign-extended constant
that's well the constant is part of our
instruction so what we do is we simply
grab those 16 bits from our instruction
will sign extend them and we'll talk in
a second about how you do that and then
you just add a multiplexer here which
has a control signal B select which is
going to be 0 if you want to do regular
ALU operations with two registers and
it's going to be 1 if you want to do an
ALU operation with a constant and so
based on the opcode we'll determine what
this V cell control signal needs to be
and then note that we actually don't
really need very much logic in order to
do the sign extension the sign extension
is just taking this bit 15 and copying
it if we're into the high order 16 bits
of your of your data path and so by just
using some wiring we can actually
implement this function of sign
extension okay so we'll take the 16 bits
from the instruction directly that 15 is
going to be replicated into bits 16
through 31 all right so now quickly what
is the data flow here look like again
very similar to before except now we
have to set B cell equal to 1 in order
to get the constant into our ALU
we have the function that's based on
that whatever the control logic told us
is the function we want the ALU to
perform and then we feed our result back
to our register file and we have worth
equal to what so what you see here is
that with a really a very relatively
simple data path we've actually just
implemented almost all of the beta
instructions okay so that's one of the
huge benefits of RISC type processors
where a RISC stands for reduced
instruction set computers where the idea
is that you instead of having very
complex instructions that might be able
to take things like memory locations as
your source a source operands you choose
to go with a simpler route and have
potentially more instructions but
simpler ones so that the hardware that
you could have to build is much much
easier to build all right so let's move
on to the load instruction to do a load
instruction we have to have our memory
here now note that this instruction
memory and data memory are actually the
same main memory if you recall when we
talked about memories we said would use
the same memory for both we just split
them up here in order to make it easier
to visualize but really just think of
this as a three port memory where you
have to read ports one of them is for
reading instructions the second is for
reading data and then you have one write
port so in order to write to the data
memory and so what happens now the
instruction that we want to execute is
shown up here and what we see is that
the calculation of the address for loads
is basically looks the same as an ADD C
instruction so we've already got the
hardware that we need in order to
produce the address and so what we have
to do is we're going to use the same
path here that we use for the add C
instruction and now the output of the
ALU instead of being feeding the right
data path of our of our of our register
file it's actually now going to be used
as the address of our data memory okay
we're also going to have some control
signals for our data memory which are
going to tell us whether we are
writing to the to the memory which is
the MWR stands for a memory right and
we're gonna have mo e which stands for
memory output enable and so we set
memory output enable to one when we want
to read from it we set memory write to
one when we want to write to it and of
course when we don't want to write we
have to make sure that this value is
zero so we don't inadvertently write
something that we didn't mean to write
into our memory and now we have a new
multiplexer that we just added to our
data path this WD cell multiplexer and
so when WD cell is equal to two we're
gonna take the value that's coming out
of our data memory as the data that's
going to be fed back into our register
file okay so so that's exactly what we
want here for the load and so we take
the value that came out of the memory at
this location and that's what's gonna
get written back into register R C so
very quickly to look at the data flow we
first follow the path of the ad Z in
order to use a sign extended constant to
add to our register RA and we do that by
making the control signal B selects
equal to 1 we then set the ALU FN to be
a plus B so that we can do the addition
of those two things in order to produce
the address for our load this address is
used to decide which location in memory
we want to read and then we set the
control signals for our memory to say I
want to read something and so memory
write is zero memory output enable is 1
and now I get the data out of my memory
I set WD cell to 2 and then that comes
back over here and finally I set Worth
to 1 in order to enable writing to my
register file ok any questions so far
good
so moving on to store store is very
similar to load in the sense that we're
going to produce the address for our
memory in exactly the same way as the
load the main difference with a store is
where our source comes from so in this
case our sources register our seat now
if you look at our data path so far
without this new piece we're about to
add we don't have a way of actually
reading the contents of register our
seat so what we're going to do is we add
this additional multiplexer here that
allows us to choose between RB and RC as
our second read operand okay and of
course it works out nicely that store
operations don't actually make use of RB
and so it's perfectly fine to take over
that port for this particular operation
so on a store our control logic is going
to be responsible for making our a to
sell equal to one for all other types of
instructions it'll make our a to sell
equal to zero so that the register B
will be the one selected out of this out
of the register file ok the other thing
we have to do is we need to add a
connection from our second data port
into the right data input of our memory
okay so what comes out of the register
file is the value that we want to write
to the memory and the last thing to note
is that we don't have this is the one
instruction for which Worth is going to
be equal to zero okay the store
instruction is the only instruction
where we don't actually write anything
back to the register file and the way
that we achieve that is by setting work
to zero and so again if we look at the
data flow through here we begin with
something like an add see instruction we
are where we said B sell equal to 1 in
order to produce the correct address in
our for our through our Lu we're gonna
have to do an ADD function in the ALU in
order to get that correct address we'll
then use that address to tell the data
memory which location we want to write
to in this case we also have to produce
the value that we want to write so we're
going to set our a to sell equal to 1
in order to have the register that's
right over here we register our C
instead of our B and then that value is
going to come out here and it's going to
go into the right data port of our
memory we have to set our control
signals accordingly so in this case we
want to set MWR to 1 because we're
writing to memory and mo e to 0 and then
we're gonna set WD cell to don't care in
this case because we're not actually
making use of either the ALU output or
the output of our data memory okay
and we're guaranteed of that because we
said worth equal to zero okay so now
note that when you actually create the
hardware for your for your beta there
will be an actual signal for a wd cell
but setting it as a don't care
essentially allows you to potentially
simplify your logic if you were to
implement your control ROM with
combinational logic not your controller
arm I mean your controlled logic okay so
we've got ALU operations of both kinds
we've got loads and stores now we want
to look at operations that change the
control flow okay and so we're going to
be back over in this portion of our
circuit which is things that affect our
program counter which instruction we're
going to fetch next so what do we need
in order to support a jump instruction
there are two things that a jump
instruction does the first is that it's
going to take the contents of register
RA and make that the new value of the PC
and in addition it's going to store the
value PC plus 4 into register RC so we
add this new path coming out of our PC
plus 4 adder and this value here is PC
plus 4 and so if we set WD cell equal to
0 will get PC plus 4 being fed back as
the data for the R register file right
and then on for selecting of the PC
we're going to have now a larger
multiplexer which for a jump you want to
set PC selects equal to 2
and the address that's going to feed it
directly into the PC is the value that's
in register RA and so we label that JT
which stands for jump target and this
value which is just the contents of RA
is fed into the second input of our
multiple cell multiplexer and so to look
through the data flow we have our PC
plus 4 value coming in here we set WD
cell equal to 0 or equal to 1 that
enables writing PC plus 4 into register
RC and then we have the RA register
coming into this jump target input of
our PC cell MUX
we set PC cell equal to 2 and that way
that's gonna be the next value that's
going to be loaded into our PC register
and then the rest of them are Doe cares
except for the MWR which we said has to
be 0 if we don't want to if we want to
ensure that we're not writing some kind
of random data into our memory ok all
right so we're almost there so now we're
onto branch instructions so what do we
need for branch instructions branch
instructions they do some some of what
the jump instruction did which is that
your PC plus 4 value is going to be
stored into register RC and so that's
going to make use of this data path
right here just like the jump did but
now the calculation of our next address
is a little bit more complicated and
what we want to do is we want to take
the PC plus 4 value that's coming out of
here and add to that 4 times the sign
extended constant and so we have a new
special register sorry a new special
adder called the branch offset a dirt
which we use in order to calculate PC
plus 4 plus 4 times sign extended
constant now note that doing the 4 times
again just like the sign extension was
something that we could just do through
wiring the 4 times is also something we
can just do through wiring basically the
way that you multiple
a number by four is you shifted to the
left by two and so that just means that
I need to make my bottom two bits be
zero and all my other two bits shifted
to the left with the sign extension
being executed as well this time for 14
bits rather than 16 and since I I'm
shifting everything to the left by 2
okay and then finally we have some
combinational logic based on our our a
register which is going to say okay if
RA is equal to 0 then the signal Z is
going to be 1 and if RA is not equal to
0 then Z is going to be 0 and we feed
this Z input to the control logic and
that's going to help us determine what
PC cell should be whether we want a
branch or not so if we're going to take
the branch we're gonna make PC Cell
equal to 1 if we're not going to take
equal to 0 all right and so let's see
the data flow for this as well so we've
got PC plus 4 coming through here we
make a WD selects equal to 0 so that
we're writing the PC plus 4 value into
register RC we come back here with that
value that gets written into register RC
with worth equal to 1 we then have what
this combinational logic here is it's a
32-bit nor ok a 32-bit nor is going to
do exactly what you want which is if all
the bits are 0 it'll produce a 1
otherwise it will produce a 0 and so
that's going to be used to generate this
z signal which is going to feed some
additional logic in our control logic
which will control whether pc select
should be 0 or 1 and then the PC plus 4
value and the 4 time sign extended
constant are coming to this new special
adder and we're producing the
destination of our branch in the case
that it's taken and that goes into the
one input of the PC cell box
and again the rest of our control
signals are don't care except for MWR
which we need to continue to ensure is
zero so that we don't write something
inadvertently to our memory okay so far
so good
excellent so we've done all of our
instructions so far
oh sorry actually one more load relative
so what is load relative load relative
is similar to a load in that it's just
going to get a piece of data from memory
the difference between load and load
relative is the way that we calculate
the address from which we're going to to
load a value and what we're doing here
if you look at this this is PC plus 4
plus 4 times sign extended constant this
is actually the output of our branch
offset adder okay so you might want to
ask yourself well what does that mean
you know to load a value using the
output of this branch offset adder and
what that means is basically that's your
loading of value from some location
that's nearby to this current LDR
instruction so you might want to ask
yourself well why would I ever want to
do that right I mean next to this
instruction I just have other
instructions so why am I going to want
to load that as a piece of data and it
turns out that there's a good reason for
it and that is if for example you have a
very large constant that will you want
to use in your program for example if we
wanted to do something like x times this
big constant 1 2 3 4 5 6 I can't fit
this constant into my 16-bit operations
so instead I have to have it stored
somewhere in memory I need to load it
into a register and then do to register
a to register a operation in order to do
that multiplication so in order to to do
this it's useful to be able to you know
to store this constant somewhere nearby
in my program and so the way that we
would do that is you would have a
special label let's call it c1 here
where you're storing this piece of data
because it's kind of part of your
program
and then if I do LDR of c1 into r1 then
that's going to load this nearby
location into register r1 okay and so so
note that that you can't just do a
regular load because you have no idea
where in your memory you are okay and
the load can only use a 16-bit constant
as its address and so you could use a
load if this if this location happened
to be something that required fewer than
16 bits to represent but if this address
was large then the way that you would
represent it is using a load relative
instruction any questions about that all
right
so the data path for a load relative is
once again we pretty much have
everything that we need the only thing
we need to add is this one additional
multiplexer so we have this a select
multiplexer which picks RA when the
value is 0 or it picks this PC plus 4
plus 4 times sign extended constant when
a select is 1 and so for a load relative
instruction we're just going to pick
this path now mr. blue over here asked a
very good question
which is if you think about what's
actually happening here because we put
this multiplexer before the ALU what
we're going to do is we're going to set
a selects equal to 1 we're going to get
the value of this branch off set adder
through here then we're gonna have to
set ALU FN to be a to just pass along
that value through our ALU and so you
could think to yourself well why not
just take this output and feed it
directly to a multiplexer over here any
ideas why you can't do why you might not
want to do that
guesses are ok
so I'll tell you why the reason is
because of wanting to minimize our clock
period okay so if I add a multiplexer
over here then that means that the
propagation delay of this multiplexer is
going to have to be included for every
single one of my operations okay because
in order to do a load or store operation
I would now have to go through this
multiplexer as well as this multiplexer
so even though you might think you know
that
oh that propagation delay is just 1 MUX
multiplexer it's not very much the
reason that it is so critical is because
it actually controls the clock cycle of
all of your operations ok so if you can
do things to shorten it then you're
gonna want to do that ok so even though
it seems a little bit more complicated
putting the a select MUX over here
allows the propagation delay of this to
occur in parallel with the B select MUX
and so now we're getting the benefit of
being able to do a load relative
instruction without paying anything as
far as performance goes okay and so
quickly we'll show the data flow here
and so we have the output of our of our
branch offset adder coming in here we
make a selects equal to 1 then we set
our ALU function equal to a to just
propagate that value through here that
becomes the address of our data memory
we then set the control signals for our
memory correctly zero because we don't
want to write one because we do want to
read the data comes out here we now set
W deselect equal to two that allows us
to get the output of our memory coming
back into our register file we set worth
equal to 1 and now this value came out
of our memory is going to be written to
wherever our C points to ok so we did
all of our instructions but there's one
more thing which we have to worry about
which are exceptions which is what do we
do when something goes wrong ok so
suppose for example that I have
the bug in my program and I made my
program fetch you know a piece of data
as if it was an instruction okay if I do
something like that then it's possible
that when I try to decode my opcode it's
going to math to some opcode that
doesn't even exist right so I need to be
able to do something reasonable in that
situation another type of problem that
can happen is suppose that I did my
calculation for my address of my memory
okay I added a register in some constant
and I produced a value and I ended up
somehow producing a value that's larger
than the size of my memory okay again
not something I can handle in my
hardware so we need to have a way of
dealing with that another type of
problem might be suppose that I try to
do a divide by 0 something that I can't
do other things that I might need to
deal with are things that aren't
actually caused by the program itself
suppose there's an external event like a
user hits a key on the keyboard
I might have to respond to the fact that
the user wants me to you know notice
that I that they hit a key and so that
is going to be dealt with through
exceptions as well and so the way that
we're going to handle exceptions is
we're going to basically do an implicit
procedure call we're gonna force a
procedure call to a special handler
which is part of our software and we're
gonna have two different kinds of
handlers one is going to be for these
cases over here which are called by our
program and another handler is going to
be for these cases over here which are
external events and the great benefit of
all of this is that we can do this in a
way that's completely transparent to our
program ok so what we would do is we
would interrupt our program we would go
off into the software handle whatever
problem it is that we have or even
execute an instruction that doesn't
exist in our instruction set
architecture and then we would come back
to our program as if nothing happened
so though you know one of the main
benefits of this is that you could in
this way also make your instruction set
architecture more complicated without
actually complicating the hardware of
the processor that you build ok so our
plan for handling exceptions is we're
going to interrupt the program we're
going to invoke this procedure call
which is going to be a handler for our
exception and then when we're done we're
going to continue with execution where
we left off and so I just briefly
mentioned that we kind of have two
situations we want to deal with we'll
call the first one exceptions which are
synchronous events there are the ones
that are caused by the program doing
something wrong so if I try to access an
invalid address in memory or if I try to
do a divide by 0 or I try to you know do
something that's an invalid opcode those
would all fall into this category the
second type are interrupts where there's
some asynchronous events like a user you
know hitting a key on a keyboard and I
need to handle those situations as well
and so I'll have two different handlers
one for each one of these two cases okay
so the way that we're going to handle it
is the first thing I'm going to do is
I'm going to save my PC plus for value
so that I can come back to where I left
off and then we're going to load the PC
with the address that's going to get me
to that Handler and so that address is
going to be for for synchronous events
and eight for asynchronous events and
then from these addresses we'll probably
will have a jump instruction to the
appropriate handler so we finally
introduced register r30
in case some of you were wondering if we
were ever going to make use of it
register r30 is what we call the
exception pointer okay so we use this
register in order to store that PC plus
for value so that we can come back to
our to our program after we're done
dealing with the with the exception
you because it's possible to get an
exception at any point in time which
would immediately overwrite your
exception pointer you have to make sure
that your user programs do not try to
use the exception pointer as a regular
register okay so a quick example of how
this would work suppose I have a piece
of code here and I try to execute a div
operation and divide which I didn't
actually implement in my hardware so
what would happen is I would cause a
call to my software which branches
basically to this handler from my ill op
stands for illegal operation handler I
would save my XP I would then figure out
which instruction it is that caused a
problem by looking at my memory in the
location pointed to by the contents of
XP minus 4 which is right with just
stored PC plus 4 into it so I subtract
it to get the actual div instruction and
once I know that then I can actually go
ahead and implement this instruction in
software I know the source and
destination operands and so I can
actually do everything that I need to do
once I'm done I pop my XP register and I
jump back there so that I can continue
execution of my program ok now note that
in the case where you're dealing with an
asynchronous event you're going to want
to actually decrement the value of XP to
go back to the instruction that it never
actually executed and and re execute it
so you would have to you know put XP
minus 4 into your XP register before you
jump to it ok and so very quickly what
does our hardware look like to support
this we add another multiplexer here
which controls what gets written which
register gets written in our register
file we call this the W a select
multiplexer and when it's 1 it may it
selects the register to write to as the
X P register we also have two additional
inputs to our PC cell MUX and so we we
send a long address for for if it's an
illegal operation and address eight if
we have an ace
this type of exception and we need to
produce the right value of her w a
select in our control logic based on
either the fact that we you know that we
figured out that it's an illegal opcode
or the fact that we got an external
interrupt request which tells us that
something like you know hitting a key on
a keyboard just occurred and so oops
sorry so if we take a look at what needs
to happen in the hardware for this we're
going to store the value of PC plus 4
into our XP registered so PC plus 4
comes in right here W deselect equals 0
that sends the PC plus 4 value over here
I set were fee equal to 1 and remember I
had to make W a Cell equal to 1 in order
to make my destination register be XP
and finally my PC cell is going to be
either 3 or 4 depending on whether it
was an illegal operation or an exception
and then the rest of them again are
don't cares except for the MWR so that's
basically our full solution and here we
just show a summary of all of these
control signals that we just talked
about for every single type of operation
that we might need to execute on our
beta and so just a couple lines that we
want to point out are specifically the
MWR note that there's no don't cares
here ok this is always set to either 0
if you don't want to read it to it from
your sorry if you don't want to write to
your memory or 1 when you're doing a
store and similarly worth is also always
0 or 1 except for in the case of a reset
where we kind of assume that we don't
need to maintain the state of our
registers if we're doing a reset ok any
questions
all right we'll have fun building your
baby